<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Vox ducis: or, An alarme from the trumpet of God to euery souldier in Iesus Christ. Calling them to fight the good fight of faith. In a sermon at Pauls Crosse, Sept. 11. 1631. by Iohn Robinson preacher of the word of God and Mr of Arts of Kings Coll. in Camb.</title>
            <author>Robinson, John, preacher.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1631</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10845</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21117</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114096</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849324</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849324</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14464</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10845)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14464)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1494:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Vox ducis: or, An alarme from the trumpet of God to euery souldier in Iesus Christ. Calling them to fight the good fight of faith. In a sermon at Pauls Crosse, Sept. 11. 1631. by Iohn Robinson preacher of the word of God and Mr of Arts of Kings Coll. in Camb.</title>
                  <author>Robinson, John, preacher.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 79, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Harper,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1631.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14464:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14464:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ox Ducis:</hi> OR, AN ALARME FROM THE TRVM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet of God, to euery Souldier in Ieſus Chriſt. Calling them to <hi>Fight the good fight of Faith.</hi> In a Sermon at Pauls Croſſe, Sept. 11. 1631.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Iohn Robinſon</hi> Preacher of the Word</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Harper.</hi> 1631.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14464:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14464:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, THE LADY ELIZABETH COVENTRY, The moſt vertuous Conſort of the thrice renowned THOMAS, Lord COVENTRY, Baron of <hi>Ailsborough,</hi> Lord Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the great Seale of <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a receiued</hi> Maxime <hi>in warre, that if the enemy be once gone forth, as the</hi> Philiſtines <note place="margin">Iudg. 16.</note> 
               <hi>were ſometimes</hi> to deſtroy, <hi>it is not then wiſdome any longer for the
<pb facs="tcp:14464:3"/>
aduerſe part to hide his ſtrength wholly in the Garriſon; As</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, <hi>we haue all ſome common enemies to fight against; and who then among vs is not engaged in the quarrell?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For me, I am the weakeſt of all</hi> Gods <hi>Worthies, yet in this common cauſe haue I been emboldned to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture my ſelfe and my</hi> forces <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the</hi> field <hi>of</hi> Chriſts Church. <hi>Giue but the Word of your graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous entertainement, they are all</hi> muſtered <hi>vp to waite vpon your</hi> Honor, <hi>and to fight for you againſt the</hi> Dragon <hi>and his</hi> adherents. <hi>Indeed</hi> Iob <hi>ſaith, that when</hi> hee went out of the gate, the young <note place="margin">Iob 29. 8.</note> men hid themſelues. <hi>And if the</hi> old Captaines <hi>be abroad, the</hi> freſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water <note place="margin">Downham his ſpiritual warfare. Gouge in 6. ad Epheſ.</note> ſouldiers <hi>will not dare to ſhew their faces: But yet if we heare the</hi> Trumpet <hi>of</hi> God <hi>ſounding out of</hi> Sion, <hi>if the</hi> faith <hi>of</hi> Chriſt, <hi>as
<pb facs="tcp:14464:3"/>
here, calling aloud vnto vs, then</hi> if I forget thee, O Ieruſalem, let my <note place="margin">Pſal. 137. 5</note> right hand forget her cunning, <hi>and</hi> let him that hath a hand, go <note place="margin">Exod. 17. 9</note> vp <hi>and</hi> ſtrike Amalecke. <hi>For the</hi> Turkes <hi>ſay well, that all cannot be</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Knolls in Hiſt. Turc.</note> Ianiſaries, <hi>well</hi> experienced <hi>men at</hi> Armes, <hi>but there is alſo ſome good vſe of their</hi> Aſapi, <hi>of their rude and</hi> inexpert rabble, <hi>if it be for nothing elſe but, with their</hi> numbers, <hi>to</hi> blunt <hi>the</hi> ſword <hi>of the</hi> Aduerſary. <hi>So the</hi> Locuſts, <hi>wee know,</hi> are a people not ſtrong, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro. 30. 27</note> 
               <hi>this,</hi> without a Generall, yet <hi>as</hi> Agur <hi>obſerued of them long ſince,</hi> do they go forth by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How much more then if the</hi> Lord <hi>hath ſpoken, as in</hi> Amos, Who <note place="margin">Amos 3. 8.</note> can but prophecie? <hi>So if our</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>bids vs</hi> charge, <hi>who can but</hi> ſhew <hi>his</hi> courage? <hi>Then will euery</hi> woman <hi>proue a</hi> Deborah, <hi>an</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazon,
<pb facs="tcp:14464:4"/>
               <hi>and forgetting her owne weakneſſe, arme her ſelfe with a</hi> maſculine <hi>valour. In this caſe, euery</hi> Mephiboſheth, <hi>euery</hi> lame ſouldier, <hi>as he is not well</hi> able to fight, <hi>ſo, though hee could, yet will not he be</hi> willing to flie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In hope then that your</hi> Honour <hi>will be pleaſed to be, as</hi> Iob <hi>ſaith of him ſelfe,</hi> Euen feet vnto the lame, <hi>I doe here moſt humbly commend</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iob 29. 15.</note> 
               <hi>him to the ſafe</hi> Banner <hi>of your</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, <hi>and crauing pardon for my</hi> entrenching <hi>thus farre vpon your Noble</hi> fauour, <hi>becauſe I am a</hi> Stranger <hi>to your knowledge, yet as a perpetuall</hi> honourer <hi>of your</hi> ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, <hi>I ſhall euer deſire to reſt,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your <hi>Honours</hi> preſt ſeruant,
IOHN ROBINSON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14464:4"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ox Ducis. <hi>1. TIMOTHIE 6. 12.</hi> Fight the good fight of faith.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S are the times warlicke and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall, agreeing right with our Sauiours <note place="margin">Mat. 24 6</note> prophecie, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the latter dayes, That there ſhall bee <hi>warres, and rumours of warres: The father,</hi> he <hi>ſhall riſe against the ſonne; and the ſonne against the father:</hi> So alſo is my Text. Onely here is the difference,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14464:5"/>
that whereas the firſt is corporall, this ſecond is ſpirituall. For <hi>wee wrestle not againſt fleſh and bloud,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eph 6 12.</note> ſaith <hi>Paul, but against principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and powers, and ſpirituall wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſes:</hi> That whereas the fight of the world is of one man againſt another: this of a Chriſtian is of one and the ſame man againſt himſelfe. <hi>Et</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Maior qui ſe quam qui caetera vincit Impetus:</hi> and they are euer the moſt dangerous enemies, ſayes our Sauiour, that are of our owne <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 36</note> houſhold. So that my Text, you ſee, is nothing elſe, but <hi>Vox Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis,</hi> The Captaines voice, whoſe voice, when he ſpeakes, is dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; and whoſe tongue is like a ſharp ſword whetted to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate; or elſe it may bee called, if you pleaſe, <hi>Tuba Militis,</hi> the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers Trumpet; but not like that Trumpet that <hi>Paul</hi> makes men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.</note>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:14464:5"/>
of, which giues a doubtfull and vncertaine ſound, for who ſhall then prepare himſelfe for the combate? But rather like the trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet of <hi>Gideon,</hi> that giues certaine <note place="margin">Iudg. 7.</note> inſtructions when we ſhall begin the fight; and that is, when it is for the Lord and for <hi>Gideon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. When it is for the Lord, when it is <hi>Profide,</hi> for the faith, <note place="margin">1. Cor. 4. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Vnus enim Dominus, vna fides,</hi> ſaid the Apoſtle in another caſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When it is for <hi>Gideon</hi> alſo, I meane for the good of euery true <hi>Gideon,</hi> of euery faithfull Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and then <hi>Pugnemus ſtrenui,</hi> it behoues vs preſently to ſtretch forth our hands to warre, and our fingers to fight.
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fight the good fight of faith.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>In the words you may pleaſe to obſerue theſe three parts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A martiall act, in this word <hi>fight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:14464:6"/>
2. The ground, or cauſe of this act, which <hi>Lipſius</hi> calls well, <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>put</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Polit. li. 5.</note> 
               <hi>bonae ſpei, quae ducit ad trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phales illas terras:</hi> The Cape of good Hope, that leads vs to thoſe fortunate Iſlands of victory: and this is, the faith of Chriſt, we muſt <hi>Dimicare profide,</hi> ſtriue for the <note place="margin">Iud 3.</note> faith. <hi>Nullum enim bellum ſaſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitur à civitate optima,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, niſi aut profide, aut pro ſalute.</hi> We muſt not fight, as the Logi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian <note place="margin">De Rep. l. 3.</note> diſputes, <hi>Pro &amp; Con, De omni themate,</hi> vpon any cauſe, vpon any occaſion; but the ground of it, that muſt alwayes be the faith of Chriſt: it muſt bee, <hi>Certamen fidei,</hi> the fight of faith.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The ſpurre to pricke vs on to this combate, and this is our owne good and wellfare, which ſits in the Text like a King in his Throne; or as the heart in the middeſt of the body, that ſo euery
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14464:6"/>
part may receiue an equall influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: for it is <hi>Bonum certamen, A good fight.</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fight the good fight of faith.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt then for the firſt part, which is the warlicke act, in this word <hi>Fight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which though it be but a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle word, and this word alſo but a ſingle ſyllable, yet <hi>Multum habet in ſe ponderis:</hi> that as the wiſe <note place="margin">Wiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 4. 16</note> man ſaith of <hi>Enoch,</hi> how hee did fulfill much in a little time: ſo may we ſay of this word, that it doth fulfill a great deale of matter in a little roome. <hi>Parvum quidem le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctu, ſed magnum intellectu:</hi> for being a tearme of art belonging properly to the campe of <hi>Mars,</hi> it doth eaſily hold out vnto vs that of <hi>Iob,</hi> That <hi>Militia eſt vita hominis ſuper terram:</hi> That the life of a Chriſtian is a warfare vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth. And if you would ſee <note place="margin">Iob 7. 1.</note>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:14464:7"/>
the Metaphor further explained, looke into the 1. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 15. 13. where we haue an exhortation of the ſame Apoſtle wholly conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of militarie tearmes, <hi>Watch ye,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>ſtand faſt in the faith, quit your ſelues like men, and be ſtrong.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the ſaying of <hi>Eliphas,</hi> that <note place="margin">Iob 5. 7.</note> 
               <hi>we are all borne to labour:</hi> and as we are borne to labour, ſo alſo to fight, <hi>In id nati vt militomus:</hi> for theſe two, me thinks, are like <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> that hold one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">Geneſ. 25 26.</note> by the heele.</p>
            <p>And therefore you may reade of the Iewes at their building of the materiall temple, that as they <note place="margin">Nehe. 4. 17</note> held a trowell in one hand, ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a ſword in the other; the one being the inſtrument of a labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, the other of a ſouldier. And thus you may thinke it alſo in the building of the ſpirituall temple.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14464:7"/>
For <hi>thinke not,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>that I am come to ſend peace on the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10 34</note> 
               <hi>earth, but rather a ſword.</hi> The confirmation of which truth, we haue from the bleſſed Virgine, who had no ſooner bore Chriſt, <note place="margin">Luk. 2. 35.</note> but preſently old <hi>Simeon</hi> tells her that a ſword muſt paſſe through her ſoule. And ſo it is with euery gracious Chriſtian, in whom Chriſt is no ſooner formed anew by faith, but preſently <hi>Audita eſt vox clamantis:</hi> A Herald at armes calls vnto him after this manner: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Come, let vs runne on to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 1.</note> 
               <hi>that is ſet before vs:</hi> for <hi>loe,</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid, how the enemies make a tumult, and conſult among</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 83. 2.</note> 
               <hi>themſelues, ſaying, Come and let vs cut them off from being a holy Nation, neither let the name of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael bee had any longer in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance. Gebal, and Ammon, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14464:8"/>
Amalecke, the Philiſtines with thoſe of Tire, Aſhur alſo is ioyned to them, and hath holpen the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Lot.</hi> Thus when Iſrael went downe to ſinfull Egypt, wee heare then of nothing but peace and whiſt; but when they begin once to leaue Egypt, and go to Canaan, to heauen and happines, then,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In ſe turbaruunt luxurioſa,</hi> then ſeuen ſeuerall nations, I meane ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen deadly ſinnes, are marching forwards to incounter them: for a remembrance whereof perhaps it was, that the Lord commanded them afterwards to keepe their feaſt of Trumpets, becauſe the <note place="margin">Leuit. 23</note> Trumpet, we know, <hi>Nil niſi bella ſonat,</hi> ſounds nothing elſe but ſad warre and deſtruction; and this hath made that part of Chriſts Church, yet remaining on earth, to be well called, <hi>Eccleſia militans,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:14464:8"/>
the fighting Church; becauſe it muſt fight the good fight of <hi>Paul</hi> in my text.
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fight the good fight of faith.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But for the better explaining of this Metaphor, two things I ſuppoſe are neceſſarie to bee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Who is our Generall, to fight vnder.</item>
               <item>2. Who our enemies to fight againſt.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The firſt of theſe alluring vs to fight, in hope of reward.</p>
            <p>The ſecond enforcing, for feare of danger.</p>
            <p>The firſt giuing vs entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>The ſecond putting vs vpon employment.</p>
            <p>For the firſt.</p>
            <p>Our Generall or Captaine, is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14464:9"/>
the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, for ſo he is called in Saint <hi>Matth.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <note place="margin">Mat. 2. 6.</note> 
               <hi>For out of thee ſhall come a Captaine,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 2.</note> 
               <hi>and the finiſher of our faith,</hi> ſaith the Author to the Hebrews.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Deus exercituum, The Lord of hoſtes,</hi> ſaith the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 1. 9.</note> 
               <hi>whoſe title is written vpon his thigh,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Iohn. Rex Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Reuel: 19. 16.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; Dominus dominantium: Hee that ſlew mighty kings,</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid, Sehon king of the Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 136. 16.</note> 
               <hi>and Og the king of Baſan.</hi> In a word, hee that ſung that trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant Paean vpon the croſſe, ouer death, hell, and Sathan; <hi>O death, where is thy ſting; O graue where</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15. 55.</note> 
               <hi>is thy victory?</hi> And this is the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptaine vnder whom wee muſt fight: <hi>The Lord is this man of warre,</hi> ſings <hi>Moſes, The Lord is his</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exod 15. 3</note> 
               <hi>mame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the ſecond.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:14464:9"/>
Now for our enemies, we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent them marching in two ranks.</p>
            <p>Either Traitours to vs, or elſe Inuaders of vs.</p>
            <p>Either Canaanites that dwell among vs, or elſe Arabians that dwell without vs.</p>
            <p>The one in the valleyes.</p>
            <p>The other vpon the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines.</p>
            <p>Take them either ſingle or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin'd, euery way ſhall you finde them very dangerous: <hi>Saul may ſlay his thouſands, and Dauid his</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 18. 17.</note> 
               <hi>ten thouſands,</hi> as the damoſells ſung: But hee that ſlayes one of theſe, doth more then they both; the fight of them being onely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt carnall, but this againſt ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall enemies: Their enemies threatning onely death to the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, but theſe death both to bodie and ſoule for euer. That as <hi>Dauid</hi> hath it, <hi>How a thouſand yeares</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 90. 4.</note>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:14464:10"/>
               <hi>with God are but as one day:</hi> ſo ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we ſay, That a thouſand of thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> enemies are not ſo much regarde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of God, as the killing of one o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> theſe; and one day in this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, is better then a thouſand in the other.</p>
            <p>Of the firſt ranke is our own<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſinfull and depraued nature; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Enemy.</hi>
               </note> enemie doubtleſſe that is much to be feared, becauſe he is <hi>De propri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lare,</hi> of our owne houſe and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and they are euer the moſt dangerous enemies, ſaith our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour: not onely <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 36.</note> the ſinne that beſets vs round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, as the Authour to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 1.</note> calls him; but farther, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The ſinne that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7. 17.</note> 
               <hi>dwells in vs.</hi> For <hi>had an open ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie done this,</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid, then</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 55. 12</note> 
               <hi>peraduenture I could haue hid my ſelfe from him,</hi> but for the ſonne of our owne wombe, our <hi>Ioab,</hi> our
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14464:10"/>
               <hi>Abſolon,</hi> our owne fleſh to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>me our enemy; whither O God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>all wee flee from this, <hi>Cum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>emit nos eadem cauſa quae ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>lit.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lypſi. de Conſt.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vna adeſt in vnis aedibus, vna</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Terent.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>bit, vna comedit, vna dormit:</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>his riſes with vs in the morning, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> keepes vs company all the day, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>d lies downe alſo with vs in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ening. And tell me then if this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>e not a dangerous enemy.</p>
            <p>2. But though the Traitour be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>iefly to be regarded, yet is not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>erefore the forrainer altogether <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be ſleighted: for if <hi>Abſolon</hi> bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>e only care of <hi>Dauids</hi> thoughts, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he iſſue of <hi>Saul</hi> will get thereby <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>o ſmall aduantage.</p>
            <p>Now our forraine enemies are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hiefly theſe two; The world, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he deuill.</p>
            <p>And firſt for the world.</p>
            <p>And if this bee not a fearefull
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14464:11"/>
aduerſary, then let all our ſenſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bee called in heere to ſpeake, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which are ſo many friends vnt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him in this outward houſe of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> bodies. It was <hi>Bernards</hi> ſpeec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Mundus obſidet me vtrinque, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <note place="margin">Medil. 14.</note> 
               <hi>per quinque portas, quinque ſcilic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> corporis ſenſus, ſagittis ſuis me vu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> nerat:</hi> The eye that lookes vpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it, and beholds nothing but van<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; the care that liſtens to it, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> heares nothing but folly; th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tongue that ſpeakes of it, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpeakes of leaſing; the taſte th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> reliſhes it, and delights in luxury<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſenſe that layes hold of it, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">Ecclus. 33.</note> giues a touch at luſt and conc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence. So that it is a very ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thing, with our Sauiour, to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the world, and yet not of it; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 1 10. &amp; 8. 23.</note> touch this pitch, and yet not to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> defiled. And therefore we read<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of our Sauiour, that when he pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for his very enemies, yet he
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14464:11"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rayes not for the world, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes <note place="margin">Ioh. 17 11.</note> that by name. <hi>Non pro <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>undo rogo, I pray not for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orld:</hi> and if it were ſuch a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous enemy to Chriſt, then muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t needs be ſo alſo to vs, becauſe <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ſeruant is not aboue his maſter.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matth. 10. 24.</note> What the Chriſtians then were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>landerouſly reported of, to bee <note place="margin">Act. 17. 6.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>roublers of the world,</hi> ſure I am, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s true in this ſenſe of the world <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owards them; <hi>Mundus enim to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us in maligno poſitus,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ohn;</hi> and therfore can be no little <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 5. 19</note> aduerſary.</p>
            <p>Now the laſt, but not leaſt, ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of a Chriſtian, is Sathan, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, The enemy as he is called, <note place="margin">Matt. 13. 25.</note> by way of eminency, as if there were no other enemies but he, or at leaſt as if he did onely hold all thoſe former wheeles in motion; like the <hi>primum mobile</hi> that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries about the other ſpheares, <hi>Sine
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14464:12"/>
me nil poteſtis facere;</hi> They being able to do nothing without him. And therefore is the fleſh called <hi>Nuntius Satanae:</hi> The deuils Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio; and the deuill himſelfe, <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12 7 Ioh. 12. 31.</note> 
               <hi>mundi.</hi> But is this, think you, all his attendants? who thinks it? For theſe two are onely his chiefe Minions, and great Fauourites. But as for his more remote and common attendants, they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable; For if <hi>Iehu</hi> do but cry, <hi>Eoquis mecum, Is there any of my</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. King 9. 32.</note> 
               <hi>ſide:</hi> as <hi>Leah</hi> then ſaid of <hi>Gad, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 30 11</note> 
               <hi>a company.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The time would bee too ſhort to tell you of all his hangbies, of <hi>Iſmael,</hi> and of <hi>Cain,</hi> of <hi>Iudas,</hi> and of <hi>Demas,</hi> of <hi>Himeneus</hi> and <hi>Phile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> of <hi>Epicurus</hi> and <hi>Nouatus,</hi> with the rabble, all which haue bound themſelues with an oath, as they did, neither to eat nor drinke vntill they haue killed <hi>Paul.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Act. 23.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:14464:12"/>
And is the life of a Chriſtian then, thinke you, a life of race, a life of pleaſure? This, I know, is <hi>Vox populi,</hi> but is it not alſo <hi>Vox ſtultorum?</hi> It is doubtleſſe. For, <hi>Heu miſeri qui bella gerunt,</hi> ſaid <note place="margin">Lucan.</note> the Poet truly; but alas, it is farre otherwiſe: for no man knowes ſo well the miſery that a ſouldier en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures, but himſelfe onely; <hi>Euery battell,</hi> as the Prophet ſpeakes, <note place="margin">Iſa. 9. 5.</note> 
               <hi>being with confuſed noyſe, and with garments tumbled in bloud.</hi> The ſouldier being alwayes, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of himſelfe, <hi>In labours more abundant then any man, in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 11. 23.</note> 
               <hi>wearineſſe and painfulneſſe, in watchings and faſtings, in cold and nakedneſſe.</hi> Beleeue me, brethren, <hi>Non eſt in terris mollis ad astra via:</hi> The way to heauen, it is not ſtrewed with ruſhes; there go vp thither no Carpet Knights, no knights of the poſt, but onely the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14464:13"/>
worthies of Iſrael, for we are all ſouldiers here. <hi>Et multa tulit mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, ſudauit &amp; alget:</hi> And the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier he hath endured many a bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter brunt amidſt the preſſe of his enemies, conſumed ſometimes like <hi>Iacob,</hi> with heate in the day, and with froſt in the night; to bee ſure, either alwayes fighting, or elſe alwayes readie to vndertake it; that ſo at laſt his enemies may be defeated, and himſelfe crowned with a triumphant Crowne of <note place="margin">Geneſ. 31. 40.</note> glory.</p>
            <p>But is it enough, thinke you, to tell you that you are ſouldiers, and therefore muſt vſe your hands to warre, and your fingers to fight, vnleſſe I teach you alſo how to fight, that ſo you may ouerthrow your enemies? No ſurely: <hi>Ideo enim bellum ſuſcipitur, vt in pace vivatur:</hi> for therefore is warre vndertaken, that you may ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14464:13"/>
your enemies, and liue in peace.</p>
            <p>Giue me leaue then, that as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 1. 18.</note> cauſed the men of Iudah to be trained vp in the art of ſhooting, ſo now alſo to traine you vp in this art of fighting, leſt elſe you fight as him that beats the aire, as the Apoſtle ſpeakes: That as <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 26.</note> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> teaches his Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians, ſo to runne that they may obtaine the prize: ſo may I teach <note place="margin">1. Cor. 9. 24.</note> you, ſo to fight that ye may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the victory:</p>
            <p>Now for the effecting hereof:</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quaedam removenda.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quaedam admovenda.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>The obſtacles to bee remoued, are either generall or ſpeciall.</p>
            <p>The generall, are all manner of ſinnes whatſoeuer; the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of ſinne, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <note place="margin">Rom. 6. 6</note> which like <hi>Amaſa's</hi> dead body, is an hindrance to vs in the purſuite
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14464:14"/>
of our victory.</p>
            <p>And therefore the Lord char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges the Iſraelites, that when their <note place="margin">2. Sam: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 12.</note> hoſt goes forth to battell, they ſhould abſtaine from euery wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <note place="margin">Deut. 13. 9.</note> thing. And this, it may bee, was the reaſon why <hi>Dauid</hi> hee <note place="margin">Pſal. 49. 5.</note> calls it, <hi>The wickedneſſe of our heeles,</hi> making ſinne like a clogge of dirt hanging at our heeles in the depth of Winter, which doth <hi>tardare greſſus,</hi> hinder vs in our march to heauen. And therefore as wee are to pray, according to our Sauiours direction, <hi>That our flight be not in the winter;</hi> ſo may <note place="margin">Mat. 24. 20.</note> we here alſo, that our fight be not at that time neither, when our feet muſt needs ſticke faſt in the mire, and cannot moue; the Iriſh bog, and the deepe way being both of them enemies as well to fighting as to flying.</p>
            <p>But more eſpecially, bee ſure
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14464:14"/>
that thou remoue thy <hi>Dalilahs,</hi> thy darling ſinne, that <hi>Primogen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Diaboli,</hi> as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> the Euangeliſt ſaid of <hi>Marc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on</hi> the Hereticke, the head of this body, euen thy <hi>Primum vivens,</hi> thy ſweet-heart ſinne, which beares rule &amp; dominion ouer this body, like a King. And therefore it was a good policie of the King of Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyria to his Captaines, <hi>Fight,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>neither againſt great nor ſmall,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 31.</note> 
               <hi>but onely againſt the king of Iſrael:</hi> Not but that he would haue them fight againſt the whole armie, but chiefly and principally againſt the King. So though we ought to ſet our ſelues againſt all that is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſinne, yet chiefly and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally againſt our maſter-ſinnes. And ſurely the king being once caught, the reſt will eaſily be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued; and hee that can ſhake off the principall, will a great deale
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14464:15"/>
more eaſily ſhake off his depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants and followers. If <hi>Holofernes</hi> be once ſlaine in his tent, though it bee by the hands of a woman, his whole armie then, be it neuer ſo numerous, will ſoone bee <note place="margin">Iudith 13.</note> brought to nothing. And the ſhepheard being once ſtrucke, the <note place="margin">Mat. 26 31</note> ſheepe will ſoone bee ſcattered. Thus wee reade of the Iſraelites, that aboue all their other ſinnes, they inſiſted chiefly in the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this great wickedneſſe, for ſo it is called, namely, <hi>In asking</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 12. 17. ver. 19.</note> 
               <hi>of a King.</hi> And as many, beloued, as are true Iſraelites, will do the like. But as for the hypocrite and counterfeit, his onely care is to ſlay ſome common ſouldier, as, murther, adultery, and the like, and then he thinkes he hath done God good ſeruice; But as for the king and ruling ſinne, that ſits in the throne of his heart, this he is
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14464:15"/>
reſolued to fight for, euen to the death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh that Iſmael might liue,</hi> ſaies he, <hi>in thy ſight: Vivat Rex,</hi> Let <note place="margin">Gen. 17. 18</note> the King liue, and all is well. For, <hi>Rege incolumi mens omnibus vna eſt; Amiſſo rupere fidem:</hi> For if the <note place="margin">Virg.</note> king be well, and the ruling ſinne, then will all other ſinnes binde themſelues by an vnanimous oath of allegiance vnto him; but as <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> ſaid, ſo he,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ioſeph is gone, and Simeon, and will ye take Beniamin too:</hi> ſo, what? <note place="margin">Ge. 42. 36.</note> haue ye forbidden mee to nouriſh other ſinnes, and will yee take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way alſo my <hi>Dalilah,</hi> my darling ſin, the ſonne of my ſtrength, of my deſires? yee ſhall then bring my gray hayres with ſorrow to the graue; for, is not the leane cattell good enough, ſaies <hi>Cain,</hi> to bee ſacrificed with the knife of mortification, but God muſt haue <note place="margin">Ge. 17. 18.</note>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:14464:16"/>
the fatteſt of the flock too? Or is <note place="margin">Gen 4. 1</note> it not great pity, ſaies <hi>Saul,</hi> that ſuch a goodly Weather as <hi>Agag</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Reg. 22</note> muſt be ſlaine? But there is a foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh pitty, ſaies the prouerb, that deſtroyes a kingdome; and if God cry, <hi>Vade &amp; percute Amaleck,</hi> yea, though he bee the firſt of the <note place="margin">Ex 17. 9.</note> Nations, and the chiefeſt in the dwellings of <hi>Ham,</hi> yet then, <hi>cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Nu. 24. 20.</note> 
               <hi>is he,</hi> ſaies the Prophet, <hi>that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ier. 48. 10</note> 
               <hi>holds his ſword from blood.</hi> Let <hi>Naaman</hi> be neuer ſuch a goodly <note place="margin">2 Reg. 5. 2.</note> man, yet if hee bee a Leper, hee muſt then be ſhut out of the hoſt; <note place="margin">Num 5. 2. Act. 10 34. Iſa. 30 33.</note> for as God is no reſpecter of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, ſo neither muſt we. <hi>Tophet is prepared of old,</hi> ſaies God, <hi>euen for the king,</hi> euen for our great and preſumptuous tranſgreſſions, and therefore this muſt alſo be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued. And ſo much for the hinderances that muſt be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:14464:16"/>
The furtherances follow.</p>
            <p>And theſe may bee conſidered, either in reſpect of our Captaine, or in reſpect of our ſelues, as ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers vnder him.</p>
            <p>In reſpect of our Captaine there be two things required.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Obedience to him.</item>
               <item>2 Imitation of him.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>1 Obedience to his word.</item>
               <item>2 Imitation of his practiſe.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And firſt for the firſt.</p>
            <p>As the word of a Generall is a ſufficient warrant to a ſouldier for the vndertaking of any warlike deſigne; And therefore <hi>Curtius,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Curt. l. 4.</note> ſpeaking of <hi>Alexanders</hi> ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, ſaies, That they were <hi>Intenti ad Ducis verbum, immo &amp; ad nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</hi> So muſt alſo the word of Chriſt our Captaine be to vs: <hi>To the Law and to the Testimonie,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 8. 20.</note> ſaies the Scripture. The Law of God that muſt bee a ſufficient te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14464:17"/>
to vs for our obedience vnto Chriſts; for as <hi>Marcus Curio</hi> ſaid concerning a diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <note place="margin">Val. Max.</note> ſouldier, whom he had put to death, <hi>Non opus eſt Reipublicae eo cive qui parere neſcit:</hi> ſo may we, <hi>Non opus eſt Chriſto eo milite,</hi> That Chriſt hath no need of ſuch a ſouldier, that knowes not how to obey him; ſince <hi>obedience is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then ſacrifice.</hi> The ſouldier he <note place="margin">1 Sa. 15. 22</note> muſt bee to his Captaine, as the ſhadow is to the body, or as that ſeruant in the Comedy was to his maſter, <hi>Ait, aio; Negat, nego.</hi> And therefore the Centurion might <note place="margin">Teren.</note> well thinke himſelfe happy in his ſeruants, when hee ſaid to one of them, <hi>Goe, and he goes; to a ſecond, come, and he comes; to a third, doe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 8. 9.</note> 
               <hi>this, and he doth it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet there bee Vndercap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains too, that muſt be obeyed as well as Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:14464:17"/>
And theſe bee either <hi>Moſes</hi> or <hi>Aaron.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Prince or Prieſt.</p>
            <p>The Magiſtrate or Miniſter.</p>
            <p>The one Gods deputy <hi>in rebus temporalibus;</hi> the other <hi>in ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualibus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore Chriſt giues the Iewes this charge concerning the Scribes and Phariſees, <hi>That what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they bad them doe, they</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 23. 1.</note> 
               <hi>ſhould doe.</hi> But yet take this cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by the way, onely ſo farre as Chriſt and they are <hi>unum agens,</hi> doe command one and the ſame thing, but no further; for elſe, <hi>whether it be better,</hi> ſaies <hi>Paul, to obey God or man, iudge yee:</hi> and <note place="margin">Act. 4. 19.</note> by this rule, ſaies our Sauiour, <hi>We cannot ſerue God and Mammon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo much for the firſt requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, in regard of our Captaine, which is obedience, in regard of his word.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:14464:18"/>
The ſecond followes, and this is imitation of him, in regard of our practiſe.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Gideon</hi> ſaid to his ſouldiers, <hi>Whatſoeuer ye ſee me doe, doe yee:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 7. 17</note> The ſame doth Chriſt to euery one of vs; and it is the duty of a good ſouldier, alwayes to follow the ſteps of his Captain: in which reſpect, S. <hi>Iohn</hi> tels vs concerning <note place="margin">Ioh. 13. 15.</note> Chriſt, that <hi>dedit nobis exemplum,</hi> that Chriſt left vs an example, that ſo wee might tread in his ſteps.</p>
            <p>But it is demanded here, <hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Q.</note> how farre the example of Chriſt our Generall muſt lead vs, and whether in all things, or no?</p>
            <p>For anſwer to which, we muſt <note place="margin">R.</note> know,</p>
            <p>That there bee ſome things wherein wee cannot follow after Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Others, wherein we may.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:14464:18"/>
Of the firſt ſort are his mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous works, as namely, his faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forty dayes; his walking vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſea, and others of like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: <note place="margin">Mat. 4. Matth. 14.</note> and hee that eſſaies now to doe theſe after Chriſt, is very like to ſtarue for hunger, or elſe to be drowned in the depths, as the Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians were, who becauſe they ſaw the Iſraelites go through the red ſea with a miracle accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, they would therefore needs follow them alſo, preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming on the like ſucceſſe: <hi>Impij autem non ſic,</hi> ſaies <hi>Dauid;</hi> for <note place="margin">Pſal. 1.</note> the text tels vs, that when they aſſayed to doe it after them, the ſea then cloſed vp her mouth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and ſhut vp their liues in deſtruction. <note place="margin">Ex. 14. 28.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It is then in our imitation of Chriſt our Generall, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeakes in another caſe of almes, <hi>Not according to that a
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14464:19"/>
man hath not, but according to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Co. 8. 12</note> 
               <hi>that a man hath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And theſe bee either naturall or morall.</p>
            <p>The naturall are ſuch as ſerue to the preſeruing of our naturall ſubſiſtence and being, as to eat, drinke, ſleepe, &amp;c. Now in theſe we cannot but follow after him, becauſe, in themſelues conſidered, they are neither good nor euill.</p>
            <p>Only morall duties then are they that we propound here vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our ſelues from Chriſt, by way of patterne and imitation.</p>
            <p>But there are Vndercaptains here alſo that muſt not bee deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
            <p>And theſe bee the glorious company of all the Prophets, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and Saints of God, that haue beene ſince the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan. And therefore <hi>Paul</hi> wiſhes <note place="margin">Phil. 3. 17.</note> the Philipians to bee followers of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14464:19"/>
him, and to looke vpon all thoſe that walke ſo as they haue him for an example.</p>
            <p>But though our Generall, and Vndercaptains muſt both bee fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, yet not both after one and the ſame manner.</p>
            <p>The one as an abſolute and perfect patterne.</p>
            <p>The other only with a <hi>quate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> ſo farre as they follow Chriſt and no further.</p>
            <p>For as man is compounded of a two fold morall principle, either fleſh or ſpirit: So alſo are his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall actions that flow from him, ſauouring accordingly, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come either good or euill.</p>
            <p>In the one we regard no mans credit whatſoeuer, but onely in the other. The credit of <hi>Iob</hi> was good in his patience at one time, <note place="margin">Iob 1. 21.</note> but not ſo in his impatience and curſing of his birth at another; <note place="margin">Iob 3. 3.</note>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:14464:20"/>
therein, <hi>dixit inſipiens,</hi> hee ſpake <note place="margin">Iob. 2. 10.</note> as his wife did, very fooliſhly. The practiſe of <hi>Dauid</hi> was imitable in <note place="margin">1. Sam. 13. 14.</note> many things, for it was after Gods owne heart: But in the matter of <hi>Vriah,</hi> there we thinke him to be a man after his owne heart, and not after Gods, and therefore dare not follow him. So was <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. King. 15 5.</note> a good man in many things, howbeit in the buſineſſe to the Embaſſadours of the King of Babylon, therin, ſaith the Text, <note place="margin">2. Chron. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 31.</note> did the Lord leaue him to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; and ſo doe we alſo. So was <hi>Lot</hi> alſo a righteous man, ſaue in <note place="margin">Gen. 19 34</note> the matter of his drunkenneſſe, and he that followes him in this, followes but a ſtaggering guide; and a thouſand to one if hee euer hit the right way to heauen. So that here that rule of <hi>Seneca</hi> is good, <hi>Quicquid ab illis bene fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum eſt, noſtrum ad imitationem;
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14464:20"/>
Quicquid male, noſtrum ad conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lationem.</hi> And now, as <hi>Vriah</hi> ſaid, <hi>What, ſhall my Lord Ioab, and the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 11. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Arke of God lie in the field, and ſhall I go home to lie with my wife? I will neuer do it.</hi> Or elſe as <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> ſpake to the children of <hi>Gad</hi> and <hi>Ruben,</hi> ſo ſay I to you, <hi>What</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Numb. 32 6.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall our brethren go forth to warre, and will ye,</hi> like idle drones, <hi>ſit ſtill in Gilead, becauſe it is a place fit for pastorage? Apage hanc amentiam!</hi> For heare what our Sauiour ſaith of ſuch, <hi>Quid ſtatis hic toto die otioſi?</hi> For what? <note place="margin">Mat. 20. 6</note> haue ye not yet receiued your hire, your peny, your preſſe-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney? O thou euill and ſlothfull ſeruant! Neither ſay within your <note place="margin">Mat. 25. 25</note> ſelues, that no man hath hired you, for heare how the <hi>Spirit and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Reu. vl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 17</note> 
               <hi>the Bride ſay, Come:</hi> yea how the faith of Chriſt, and our owne wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare alſo ſaith it in the Text; come
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14464:21"/>
then and let vs all go vp together, as one man, to fulfill my Text, euen to fight this good fight of faith: <hi>Fight the good fight of faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Aduerſaries then, mee thinkes, doe very ill to diſcarde theſe Captaines out of their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and to ſet a rabble of lame and blinde ſouldiers in their roomes.</p>
            <p>Among the firſt ranke we place <hi>Ignatius Loiola,</hi> the father of their Ieſuites; they that ſpeake the beſt <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in Flanders.</note> of him, ſay that he was but a lam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſouldier, and it may be he caugh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his lameneſſe, as <hi>Mephib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſheth</hi> did his, by falling from his Nurſe: <note place="margin">2. Sam 4. 4</note>
            </p>
            <p>Among the ſecond, wee plac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Saint <hi>Dominicke,</hi> Saint <hi>Francis</hi> and many other of their mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> eaſie Saints, who if they had ſtrength for execution, yet wanted they ſight for direction. And i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may be they loſt their ſight, as old
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14464:21"/>
               <hi>Toby</hi> loſt his, by the Swallowes <note place="margin">Tob. 2.</note> dung of that Papall neſt. And thinke you that the battell will not go well forward with ſuch Leaders? or that if they pace after ſuch Captaines, they will not fall before their enemies? They will doubtleſſe. For <hi>if the blinde leade the blinde,</hi> ſaith our Sauiour, <hi>they muſt needs both fall into the ditch.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 15.</note> And therefore the blinde man in the Goſpell, that miſtooke men for trees, you'le ſay, would haue <note place="margin">Mar. 8. 24.</note> made but a bad Leader. But the deuill himſelfe hath a good anſwer for theſe, as he had for thoſe <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoniſtes</hi> that tooke vpon them to adiure by the name of Ieſus, <hi>Ieſus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Act. 19. 15.</note> 
               <hi>we know, and Paul, and the Saints of God, but who are ye?</hi>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And ſo much for the further ances to make our fight ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſefull in regard of our Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptaine whom we ſerue.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:14464:22"/>
Wee come now to thoſe that concerne our ſelues, as ſouldiers vnder him. And theſe reſpect,</p>
            <p>Either the matter of our fight.</p>
            <p>Or elſe the manner of it.</p>
            <p>For the Matter of our fight there is required:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Armour to fight in.</item>
               <item>2. Weapons to fight withall.</item>
            </list>
            <p>For without theſe two mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialls, it is impoſſible that wee ſhould euer ſtand before our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. And therefore it was a good policie of the Philiſtines, for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> keeping vnder of the Iſraelites, to let no Smith liue among them, whereby any warlicke materialls <note place="margin">1. Sam. 13. 19.</note> might be procured, as well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that without theſe, they could neuer effect any great matters; for the want of which, they might well be ſcoffed at by their enemies, vnder the name of <hi>Iudaei imbecil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,</hi> weake Iewes, as at the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">Nehe. 4. 2.</note>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:14464:22"/>
of the Temple. And therefore when it once came to this paſſe, That there was neither ſhield nor ſpeare among fourty thouſand of Iſrael; then was it a fit time, as <hi>Deborah</hi> ſung, to haue <hi>warre in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he gates.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iudg 5 8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>For armour then this is the firſt materiall that wee require in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouldier, who would be victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
            <p>And therefore we reade in the Goſpell, that when a ſtrong man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nters on an houſe, the firſt thing <note place="margin">Luk. 11. 22.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e will do, is to take away his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour wherein hee truſts. Indeed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e truſt much to our armour in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he battell, which made <hi>Achilles</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat he would neuer vndertake a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ombate without his harnes; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>herefore are they called, <hi>Arma <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>b arcendo hoſte,</hi> as <hi>Varro</hi> will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aue it. But yet is this of no auaile neither, vnleſſe it be alſo compleat
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:14464:23"/>
and whole; for ſo the Apoſtl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wills vs, <hi>Put on,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the whol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eph. 6. 17</note> 
               <hi>armour of God:</hi> for if we lay ope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at any one part, there will the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill be ſure to ſtrike.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quaque patet fera regnat Ery<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis:</hi> And for this reaſon may he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> well be called <hi>Beelzebub, i. e.</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Prince of flyes, becauſe the fly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> will euer light vpon the wounde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> place.</p>
            <p>And yet how many bee ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> now adayes, that lay one part o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 10. 25</note> other ope to the deuils blow, fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> want of this complete furniture<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and ſo are eaſily wounded. As</p>
            <p>One there is that hath not th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> head-peece of Diuine wiſedom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> on, and ſo layes his head too fair<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to receiue the deuils ſtroke. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thus our grandmother <hi>Eue,</hi> ſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was wounded; <hi>Ingenio perijt (h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeri)</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen 3. 6.</note> 
               <hi>ipſa ſuo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſecond, hee lyes open at the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:14464:23"/>
eyes, by not putting before them <hi>Iobs</hi> couenant; and ſo <hi>Achan</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iob 31. 1.</note> periſhed, <hi>Vt vidit, perijt:</hi> He ſaw a wedge of gold, ſaith the Text, <note place="margin">Ioſ. 7. 21.</note> 
               <hi>Videnſque concupivit, &amp; concupiſ cens abſtulit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A third, he lookes not to his hands, to hold them vp to God in prayer. And ſo <hi>Moſes</hi> was in fault;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſis manus erant graues,</hi> ſaith the Text, and thus <hi>Amaleck,</hi> you <note place="margin">Exo. 17. 12</note> know, had almoſt got the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. And laſt of all (for I haue here a large field to march in) another lookes not to the foot of his affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, as <hi>Solomon</hi> aduiſes him, but hath <hi>Tranſitum pedis,</hi> a hole <note place="margin">Prou. 4. 26.</note> there for the deuill to enter. And ſo was <hi>Achilles</hi> foild and ſlaine. Our Chriſtian armour therefore muſt be complete and whole, <hi>Put on the whole armour of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what is armour to fight in,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14464:24"/>
vnleſſe we haue alſo weapons to fight withall.</p>
            <p>Looke but into Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, and there you ſhall finde <note place="margin">Eph. 6. 12</note> enough to furniſh you.</p>
            <p>Some for defence of thy ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Some for offence of others.</p>
            <p>For defence, thou haſt theſe foure to couer the foure chiefe parts of thy body. As,</p>
            <p>For thy Ioynes, thou haſt the Girdle of truth.</p>
            <p>For thy breaſt and heart, the ſhield of faith.</p>
            <p>For thy head, the Helmet of ſaluation: and</p>
            <p>For thy feet, the ſhoes of peace to couer them from cold and harmes, as it is written: <hi>Quam ſpecioſi pedes praedicantis pacem.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 52 7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But for offence, thou haſt onely one, to wit, The word of God, which is the ſword of the Spirit, To note that we muſt be <hi>Tardi ad
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14464:24"/>
percutiendum,</hi> receiuing foure blows, rather then giuing one. But if the faith of Chriſt lyes once at the ſtake, as it doth at this time in the Text, then <hi>Vade &amp; percute Amaleck,</hi> then <hi>let him that hath</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exo. 17. 9.</note> 
               <hi>no ſword,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>go ſell his garment and buy one:</hi> Then draw thy ſword <hi>Peter</hi> out of thy ſheath, and make it drunke in the bloud <note place="margin">Luk. 21. 36</note> of thine oppoſers.</p>
            <p>For it may as well bee ſaid of <note place="margin">Mat. 26.</note> this weapon in generall, as of <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liahs</hi> ſword in particular; <note place="margin">1. Sam. 21. 9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Non eſt huic ſimile,</hi> That there is no offenſiue weapon like to this. Indeed <hi>Dauid</hi> mentions a bow as well as a ſword. <note place="margin">2. Sam. 1. 18</note>
            </p>
            <p>But yet this is onely vſefull for thoſe enemies that are afarre off, and therefore are leſſe to bee fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; But if once thoſe ſpirituall Philiſtines of ours be come vpon, as they were ſometimes on <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 16.</note>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:14464:25"/>
to deſtroy, then <hi>Gladius Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini,</hi> muſt be <hi>Gladius Gideonis,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iud. 7. 10.</note> Then muſt the ſword of the Lord be the ſword of <hi>Gideon.</hi> I meane of euery true faithfull Chriſtian</p>
            <p>And therefore as the ancient Romanes did worſhip Victory for a Goddeſſe, ſo did the <hi>Alani</hi> alſo, ſaith <hi>Marcellinus,</hi> worſhip the ſword for a God, as the chiefe meanes to attaine the victory: <hi>for the word of God,</hi> ſaies the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>is quick and powerfull, yea,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 4. 12.</note> 
               <hi>ſharper then any two-edged ſword, peircing euen to the diuiding aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the ſoule and ſpirit, of the ioints and marrow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And theſe are our weapons to fight withall, of which wee may ſay as Chriſt did of <hi>Peters</hi> two ſwords, <hi>ſatis eſt,</hi> here are enough to furniſh a Chriſtian ſouldier. <note place="margin">Luc. 22. 38</note>
            </p>
            <p>Where then are thoſe Popiſh weapons of the Church of <hi>Rome,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14464:25"/>
viz.</hi> their Croſſe, their Holy wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, their conſecrated Oyle, and the like. Surely, as the Apoſtle <note place="margin">Rom. 3. 27.</note> ſaies of works, ſo may we ſay of them, <hi>they are excluded:</hi> but by what law? by the law of faith: Our faith will not admit them, our Religion will not beare them: and why? <hi>ſilent ikter arma leges;</hi> becauſe the law of God, which is <hi>regula fidei,</hi> the rule of our faith, and our law of armes, makes no mention of them, and no maruell, for as the Apoſtle ſaid in another caſe, <hi>The Law is ſpirituall, but I am carnall:</hi> ſo ſay I, the Law of <note place="margin">Rom. 7. 14</note> God ſpeakes only of ſpirituall weapons, but are not theſe car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall? they are doubtleſſe; and thinke wee then that they are not pitifull ſcare crowes to put to flight a ſpirituall aduerſary? Alas, we may ſay of them, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet doth of the Aegyptian hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:14464:26"/>
               <hi>They are fleſh, and not ſpirit,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 31. 3.</note> 
               <hi>ſarcaſmi Diaboli,</hi> as <hi>Chemnitius</hi> well calls them, euen gugawes to make the Deuill laugh; ſo that God hath giuen them vp to ſtrong deluſions, becauſe they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without law in theſe things, yet will needs bee a law to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues; <note place="margin">Rom. 3. 14.</note> and therefore we may well feare, that as the Prophet ſpake of the Aegyptians, ſo it may be ſaid of them alſo, <hi>That both they and their weapons ſhall goe both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into hell;</hi> for hee that ſits in <note place="margin">Eze. 32. 17</note> hell, ſhall laugh at theſe weapons, Sathan ſhall haue theſe weapons <note place="margin">Iob. 41. 17. 29.</note> in deriſion.</p>
            <p>But enough concerning the matter of our fight.</p>
            <p>The manner followes.</p>
            <p>And to make this good there be three ſpeciall things required in it, which like thoſe three migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Dauid</hi> will breake through
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:14464:26"/>
an hoſt of enemies, and bring <note place="margin">1 Sam. 23.</note> from thence the water of life.</p>
            <p>The firſt of theſe is <hi>Wiſdome,</hi> and therefore <hi>Paul</hi> who was <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les veteranus,</hi> an old beaten ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, aduiſes his Epheſians <hi>to walk circumſpectly, not as fooles, but as</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5. 15.</note> 
               <hi>wiſe.</hi> So we muſt alſo fight cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpectly, not as fooles, but as wiſe: it muſt not be like the cock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braind march of <hi>Iehu,</hi> concerning whom the Scripture ſaies, <hi>that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Reg 9. 20</note> 
               <hi>he marched furiouſly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I place <hi>wiſdome</hi> in the firſt place, becauſe the Wiſe man, he tels vs, that it is the principall thing. And <note place="margin">Pro. 4. 7.</note> againe, comparing it in another place with wiſdome, he tels vs in plaine tearmes that of the Poet,
<q>
                  <l>Eſt acri potior bello prudentia dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra. <note place="margin">Eccl. 9. 18.</note>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>wiſdome</hi> is better then ſtrength. From whence it came to paſſe, ſaies <hi>Plutarch,</hi> that the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:14464:27"/>
old <hi>Spartan,</hi> if hee conquered his enemy by force, he did then offer onely a Cocke, but if by wiſdome, hee did then offer an Oxe, as a greater ſacrifice then the former. But <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> he goes yet further, and will haue it to bee <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the only virtue and captaine of a ruler.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaies he in the ſecond of his Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques, which was the reaſon why <hi>Dauid</hi> was elected of <hi>Saul,</hi> to bee the chiefe ouer his men of warre, <hi>becauſe he behaued himſelfe wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Sa. 18. 5.</note> ſaies the Text.</p>
            <p>And indeed, as want of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and diſcretion is a great want in any calling, ſo moſt ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the military, in as much as our life ſtands alwaies there vpon a moſt tickle point, that if a foole turne ſouldier, it may well be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that hee will either hold his
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:14464:27"/>
weapon flat way; and ſo wound himſelfe, or elſe miſtake his friend inſtead of his aduerſary. But for ſuch, me thinks, a Schoole of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence were better, wherein to learne skill, then a field to put it in practiſe, becauſe wrath carries ſuch to valor, and not knowledge, and therefore in fighting doe they ſeeke rather to periſh, then to vanquiſh.</p>
            <p>But it is here demanded where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this military wiſdome of a Chriſtian ſouldier doth conſiſt.</p>
            <p>In anſwer to which, I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre it to three chiefe members of the body.</p>
            <p n="1">1 To the feet, they muſt bee held in with order, that ſo they doe not range out of their proper place, according to that of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, A wiſe man will order his ſteps, but the fooliſh, hee goes out</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro. 19. 3.</note> 
               <hi>of his owne ranke, and peruerts
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:14464:28"/>
his way.</hi> And ſo wee muſt fight orderly: all of vs muſt ſet our feet in battell aray, and continue there in our ſtanding, like the Northern army, concerning whom wee read, that they ſhould runne like mighty men, and climbe the wals <note place="margin">Iocl 2.</note> like men of warre, that they ſhould march euery one in his way, and not breake their ranks. The Philoſopher could ſay that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; that <note place="margin">Ariſt. Polit. lib. 2.</note> order was the mother and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of all things; for which cauſe the Apoſtle will haue all things to be done in order, <hi>for God,</hi> ſaies the ſame Apoſtle, <hi>is the God of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and not of confuſion.</hi> As for <note place="margin">1 Co. 14. 40</note> diſorder, that dwels only in hell, the place of all miſery; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Babel</hi> is made a type of it, which ſignifies nothing but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion. <note place="margin">Gen. 11. 9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But order muſt bee on earth, as
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:14464:28"/>
in other things, ſo more eſpecially in fighting <hi>Nam cum miles Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioni, Centurio Tribuno obſequitur,</hi> ſaies <hi>Tacitus, facile fit aditus ad</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Annal, l 1.</note> 
               <hi>victoriam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>è contra,</hi> nothing ſooner loſes the field, then when men goe out of their orders and ranks, out of their places and callings, as when the maſter goes on foot, and the ſeruant gets vp into the ſaddle, which was one of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccl 10. 7</note> euils that hee ſaw vnder the Sunne, when one goes vp to the front, that ſhould come behinde in the reare;
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vſque adeo turbatur agris.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Virg, Eclog</note>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>By this meanes doth confuſion march into the army, and after it deſtruction. And indeed all now will be Captaines to teach others, when as the Apoſtle ſaies, <hi>they haue more need to be taught them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 5. 12.</note> or elſe they will haue none
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:14464:29"/>
of the Crowne, no, nor fight one ſtroke in the combat. That as it was ſaid of the Egyptians, that all of them would be Prieſts, ſo of theſe times; <hi>Moſes</hi> wiſh is now <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aegypti Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotos omnes.</hi> Nu. 11 29</note> well nigh fulfilled, <hi>Omnes erimus Caeſares,</hi> all of vs would faine bee Captains; oh that I were a King, ſaies <hi>Abſolon.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Sa. 15. 4.</note>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Regis ad exemplum totus componi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur orbis.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aut Caeſar, aut nullus.</hi> But <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolon</hi> muſt firſt learne what it is to be a ſubiect, for,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Non noſti longas Regibus eſſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus?</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>For doſt thou not know that Kings muſt haue long hands to guide the reines of gouernment?</p>
            <p>And yet now will euery Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler finde fault with the face of the picture, when his art reaches no higher then the foot: as <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid, <hi>Vnuſquiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> habet in ſe Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am;</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:14464:29"/>
But doth not hee take too much vpon him, O ye ſonnes of <hi>Levi, datur vobis ſeire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nunquid enim &amp; Saul inter</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Sa. 10. 11</note> 
               <hi>Prophetas?</hi> well, if hee be, <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus illum invaſit malus, &amp; prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabat;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Sa. 18. 10.</note> an euill and diſordered ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit hath put him into orders, and behold he prophecies; <hi>Quis au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Sa. 10. 12</note> 
               <hi>pater,</hi> as they ſaid of <hi>Saul?</hi> for is hee not the ſonne of <hi>Kiſh,</hi> who went about to ſeeke his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Aſſes, and how then doe wee heare theſe things of him? <hi>Proh pudor, Quis, Cui?</hi> as it was ſaid of <hi>Arſacius,</hi> an vnlearned Biſhop, that ſucceeded <hi>Origen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Euery curſed bramble now will take vpon him to bee a Prince a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong <note place="margin">Iudg. 9. 15</note> the trees, as in <hi>Iothams</hi> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and <hi>the ſonne of the Thiſtle muſt needs match with the Cedars</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Kin. 14. 9</note> 
               <hi>daughter.</hi> For will not this wood, ſaies hee, ſerue as well to make
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:14464:30"/>
ſome throne for a king, as ſome plaſh for a hedge? Are not all the people holy, ſayes <hi>Corah?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Nu. 16 3.</note> 
               <hi>Are not Abanah and Pharphar, riuers of Damaſcus,</hi> ſaies <hi>Naaman</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Reg 5 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> to <hi>Eliſha, as good to waſh, in as the riuer of Iordan?</hi> So are not we, ſay they, as fit to bee made Captains as other men? No, ſaies <hi>Eliſha,</hi> it muſt be <hi>Iordan,</hi> and no other riuer; the virtue of healing is annexed by God only to that riuer, and the King hee can only co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e this ouerflowing euill. As for others, <hi>nemo te conduxit ad hoc o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi> this is enough, that no man hath hired them to this work. <note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et naſci à principibus fortuitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And euery one cannot bee borne to this dignity; how then can yee expect wages for it, ſince euery one ſhall receiue his wages <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, according to his work. Rather bee ordered by
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:14464:30"/>
your Captains, <hi>&amp; quo in loco es conſtitutus, ibi aſtes,</hi> and fight in that part of the battell wherein they haue placed thee; for as Chriſt ſaid to his Diſciples in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other caſe, <hi>non veſtrum eſt ſcire myſteria regni;</hi> ſo ſay I, <hi>ſcire tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um nihil eſt.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 13. 11</note>
            </p>
            <p>Alas, you are more brute then any men, as <hi>Hagar</hi> ſaid of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, neither is there any know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge touching theſe affaires <note place="margin">Pro 30 2</note> lodging in you.</p>
            <p>Wherefore as Chriſt ſaid to <hi>Peter,</hi> ſo ſay I, <hi>quid hoc ad te?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aliud plectrum, aliud Sceptru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 21 23.</note> as <hi>Stratonicus</hi> the Muſician told <hi>Ptolemy;</hi> or as <hi>Baſil</hi> ſaid to the Emperors Steward, who laboured to peruert Scripture for the ſtrengthning of the Arian hereſy, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> It is thy part, ſaies he, to looke to the Emperors kitchin ſtuffe, and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:14464:31"/>
not to trouble thy head about the knotty places of Scripture. <hi>Vobis hoc non datur;</hi> for as the twelue Apoſtles ſaid, <hi>Is it meet to leaue the word of God and ſerue tables?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Acts 6. 2.</note> ſo may wee ſay on the contrary, is it meet, thinke you, to leaue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and come preſently to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence the word? no ſurely; for there is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a great gulfe of difference betwixt theſe two, <note place="margin">Luc. 16. 26</note> ſo that thoſe idle drones that would paſſe from hence to them, cannot, neither againe can thoſe thredbare &amp; pragmaticall tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that would from thence to vs: indeed ſome Enthuſiaſts of late daies haue not been afraid to paſſe this latter gulfe; but who ſo bold, ſaies the prouerb, as blinde Bayard; <hi>Partus enim indicavit patrem,</hi> for their vncouth births haue ſhew'd their breeding, and their roauing diſcourſes haue laid
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:14464:31"/>
them open what they were, well enough, <hi>viz.</hi> ſtragling ſheepe, diſordered men, and wandring ſtarres, as <hi>Iude</hi> ſpeakes, for when <note place="margin">ver. 12.</note> the Text hath called for brick, theſe men haue come with ſtraw in their hands, like thoſe builders of <hi>Babel</hi> and confuſion, <hi>at quis haec</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen 11.</note> 
               <hi>requiſivit?</hi> and when that hath called for tile, they haue come with ſtubble, and haue giuen thereby this witneſſe of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, <hi>I am no Prophet, but a husbandman, for man taught mee</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Zac. 13. 14</note> 
               <hi>to be ſo from my youth,</hi> ſo ſaid <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary,</hi> you know, who had an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate call from heauen to that ſacred office; and if they can ſhew the ſame patent, they may paſſe freely. <hi>At da mihi talem,</hi> as <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> ſaid of yong <hi>Timothy, &amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go cibabo auro, &amp; potabo halſamo.</hi> No, no, immediate cals are now paſt, ſo are extraordinary ſignes,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:14464:32"/>
and he that ſeekes now for ſuch a ſigne, is but an adulterous gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, ſaith our Sauiour, but no <note place="margin">Luk 11. 29</note> ſigne ſhall be giuen him, ſaue one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this, Go <hi>ſow, and</hi> then <hi>reape,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. King 19. 29.</note> 
               <hi>plant vineyards, and then eate the fruit thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>All members,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>haue not one and the ſame office:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom 12. 4.</note> but God hath made ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, ſome Apoſtles, others E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſts, &amp;c. ſo ſay I, all that ſight in the battell, haue not one and the ſame ranke, but ſome are Captains, others Colonels, others Sergeants, and others againe common Souldiers, and ſuch as do attend vpon the baggage. Are <note place="margin">1. Cor. 12. 19.</note> all Prophets, are all Apoſtles, are all Teachers, are all Captaines, are all Colonels, are all Sergeants? If all were the eye, then where were the hearing? So if all were Captaines, then where were the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:14464:32"/>
Colonells? or if all were theſe, where then were the common ſouldier and attender on the bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage? But God hath appointed, as to euery member in the body, ſo to euery ſouldier in the field his right place, his proper <hi>Vbi,</hi> that ſo there may bee no ſchiſme in the body, no diſorder in the Campe. <hi>Hee ſhall keepe thee in all thy wayes,</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid:</hi> Euery man <note place="margin">Pſal. 91. 11</note> then hath his proper ranke, his calling, his way; and God hath ſaid to him in his entrance into it, as in <hi>Iſaiah, This is thy way, walke</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 33. 21.</note> 
               <hi>in it, and thou ſhalt finde reſt to thy ſoule.</hi> But if thou once preſume to depart out of it, without licence from thy Captaine, thou haſt then no promiſe of protection at all. And therefore the deuill, ſaith learned <hi>Iunius,</hi> was but a bad So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſter, in alledging to Chriſt, Gods promiſe for preſeruation,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:14464:33"/>
without annexing vnto it the <note place="margin">Mat. 4. Pſal. 91.</note> condition of walking in his waies: It being nothing elſe, ſaith he, but <hi>Fallacia Diuiſionis,</hi> a fallacie of diuiſion, in ſeparating thoſe things that muſt be ioyned; The way of God and his protection in it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as nearely linked together, as mercy and truth that kiſſe each other. For as <hi>Bernard</hi> well gloſſes the place, He keepes vs, <hi>In vijs, non in praecipitijs,</hi> in our wayes, and not in our downefalls: So that if Chriſt had throwne him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe downe, hee had then beene quite out of Gods way, and ſo out of all promiſe of his protection, For,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Extra viam nulla ſecuritas:</hi> for out of the way is nothing but er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, nothing but danger. And therefore the Lord threatens the Iewes, that becauſe they did not know his way, but went out of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:14464:33"/>
thoſe bounds that hee had ſet them, therefore <hi>a Lyon out of the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ier. 5. 6.</note> 
               <hi>forreſt ſhould ſlay them, and a woolfe of the euenings ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure them.</hi> Indeed the ſluggard ſaith, <hi>Leo eſt in via,</hi> That there is a Lyon in the way, but how foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly? <note place="margin">Pro. 22. 12.</note> for I am ſure that he walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>In via devia,</hi> in a croſſe and by-way, when hee met with the diſobedient Prophet, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſlew him. <note place="margin">1. King. 13.</note>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And ſo much for the firſt branch of our militarie wiſedome, which was referred to our feet, and this was order to keepe them from ſwaruing.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond branch of our wiſedome followes, and this ſhall be referred to our eyes, they muſt be held open by walking; and ſo we muſt fight with a heedy and watchfull eye: according to that of <hi>Solomon,</hi> That <hi>a wiſe man hath</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 2. 14.</note>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:14464:34"/>
his eyes in his head, hee is euer watchfull, and not like thoſe of Laiſh, that were a careleſſe and <note place="margin">Iudg. 18. 67.</note> drowſie people. And therefore the ancient Romanes, in their coynes inſcribed to <hi>Mars</hi> the God of warre; did vſually ioyne a Cocke with him, which is the embleme of watchfulneſſe. And good reaſon we ſhould be watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Whether wee reſpect our owne diſpoſition; or,</item>
               <item>2. The diſpoſition of our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſary.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. Our owne diſpoſition, as now moſt prone to ſleepe, and therefore Saint <hi>Peter</hi> aduiſes vs to watch, <hi>becauſe the end of all things</hi> 
               <note place="margin">P. Pet. 4. 7.</note> 
               <hi>is at hand.</hi> Now as the nearer the day draws to an end, the more apt are men to ſleepe; So the nearer the day of this world is a drawing to his laſt period, the more are we
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:14464:34"/>
inclining to ſnorting and ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and we haue euer good cauſe to ſuſpect that we are moſt incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto, becauſe <hi>Nitimur in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titum,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom 7. 19.</note> the euill we ſhould not do, that we do. And therefore wee reade of <hi>Abraham,</hi> that when the Sunne was going downe, a deepe <note place="margin">Gen. 15. 12.</note> ſleepe fell vpon him; Now if S. <hi>Iohns</hi> age was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the laſt <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2. 18.</note> houre of the day, then muſt this wherein we liue, needs be the laſt minute of that houre. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no maruell if now, with the diſciples of Chriſt, we be ſo will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">Mat. 26.</note> to ſleepe and take our reſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If we reſpect the diſpoſition of our aduerſary, and therefore S. <hi>Peter</hi> againe aduiſes vs to watch, <note place="margin">1. Pet. 5. 8.</note> becauſe our <hi>aduerſary, the deuill, walks about like a roaring Lyon, ſeeking to deuoure vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Hee is our aduerſary, and therefore we muſt watch, for
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:14464:35"/>
we muſt not truſt our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, ſaith the ſonne of <hi>Sirach,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 12. 10</note> becauſe <hi>as iron rusts, ſo is his wickedneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. He is a ſtrong aduerſarie, as the Lion is the ſtrongeſt of all the beaſts of the field. For <hi>if</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro. 30. 30.</note> 
               <hi>the Lyon roare,</hi> ſaith <hi>Amos, ſhall</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Amo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 3. 8.</note> 
               <hi>not all the beaſts of the field tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? Etquae poteſtas comparetur ci,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iob</hi> of him, vnder the <note place="margin">Iob 41 33.</note> Metaphor of a Whale?</p>
            <p n="3">3. He is a watchfull aduerſarie, as the Lyon is ſaid to ſleepe with his eyes open: for which cauſe, ſaith <hi>Pierius,</hi> did the Egyptian Prieſts make the Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Hieroglyphick of watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe: <hi>Et vigilat hoſtis,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auſten, &amp; tu dormis? virtu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; ab hoſte probatur.</hi> O diſdaine not to learne that is good, euen <note place="margin">Ouid.</note> from thy aduerſary, and bee thou as carefull for thine owne
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:14464:35"/>
preſeruation, as the deuill is for thy deſtruction.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He is alſo a painfull aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, for he walkes about, ſaith the Text. The originall word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Magnus quidem</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iob 1. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Peripateticus,</hi> a great Peripate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, for his walke is, <hi>In cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuitu,</hi> as in <hi>Iob;</hi> It is <hi>motus circularis,</hi> which knowes no end, but is ſtill in action, and like the Phariſaicall Ieſuite, will <note place="margin">Mat. 13. 15</note> compaſſe Sea and Land to make a Proſelite. And thinke we that Sathan will do all this to no end and purpoſe? No ſurely, he doth it,</p>
            <p n="5">5. To this end, namely, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy vs, to deuoure vs, for his mouth is an open ſepulcher, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeakes of the wicked: <note place="margin">Pſal 75. 9.</note> and the graue, ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> is <note place="margin">Pro. 30. 16.</note> vnſatiable. Now if <hi>Saul</hi> bee a ſleepe, it is then eaſie enough
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:14464:36"/>
for <hi>Dauid</hi> to take away his <note place="margin">1. Sam. 26 11.</note> ſpeare, and his water-pot from him: For <hi>while the Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 13. 25</note> 
               <hi>ſlept,</hi> ſaith the Text, <hi>then came the enemy and ſowed his tares.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a Prouerbe in the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands, That when the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard ſleepes, the Deuill rocks the cradle; Sure I am, that is true in our ſpirituall warfare al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo here below, That when we ſleepe, like <hi>Ionas,</hi> in the cradle <note place="margin">Ionas 1.</note> of ſecurity, that then Sathan, <hi>Hoſtis ille Catholicus,</hi> that vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall enemy of all mankinde, is moſt buſie in plotting our deſtruction: And ſo <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeakes of him, vnder the Metaphor of a Whale, when he calls him, The <hi>king ouer all the children of pride.</hi> And it is eaſie here al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <note place="margin">Iob 41. 34.</note> to make application; all which giues truth to that of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:14464:36"/>
the Poet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Invadunt vrbem ſomno vin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irg.</note> 
               <hi>ſepultam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus it befell <hi>Balthazar,</hi> for when his eyes were, in the Poets phraſe, <hi>Somno vinoque graues,</hi> heauie through wine and ſleeping, <hi>Darius</hi> he enters the gates of the Citie, ſtanding open for deſtruction.</p>
            <p>And ſo much for the ſecond branch of our Military wiſdome, which was referred to the eyes, they muſt bee held open with watchfulneſſe.</p>
            <p>The third and laſt followes, which ſhall bee referred to the head, this muſt bee held vp by wiſedome and diſcretion <hi>(i.)</hi> we muſt rightly diſcerne betwixt the head of the body, and other infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour parts, that ſo if we put any to the hazard, it muſt be they that are leſſe principall; but as for the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:14464:37"/>
head, which like the Tower of <hi>Dauid,</hi> hath a ſuperintendencie aboue the reſt, this muſt be ſure to be warded, according to that of our Sauiour, <hi>Bee wiſe as ſerpents.</hi> Now the chiefe wiſedome of the <note place="margin">Mat 10. 16.</note> Serpent, ſaith <hi>Pliny,</hi> conſiſts in this, <hi>viz.</hi> in ſauing of his head: ſo aboue all, muſt we be ſure to hold Chriſt Ieſus, who is <hi>Caput &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſor fidei,</hi> The head and defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of our faith vnwounded, our Captaine vntouched, to hold the fundamentals of our Religion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiolate, the foundation of holines vnraced; whatſoeuer become of the hay or ſtubble that we build vpon it, and then Saint <hi>Paul</hi> tells vs, That although we ſuffer a little loſſe thereby, yet ſhall our ſelues <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3. 15.</note> be ſaued.</p>
            <p>And yet I would not haue you thinke, that we can euer be ſtrickt enough, either in our faith or
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:14464:37"/>
manners, God forbid, for the word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Epheſians, (i.) <hi>walke accurately,</hi> as the beſt <note place="margin">Eph. 5. 15.</note> Expoſitors render the word; or elſe <hi>ſtraightly,</hi> as others: and therefore <hi>Dauid</hi> tels vs that hee <note place="margin">Pſal. 115.</note> held ſtraight all the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. But yet, as <hi>Solomon</hi> doth well diſtinguiſh betwixt mirth and madneſſe, ſo doe wee heere, <note place="margin">Eccl. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 2.</note> only ſanctity from ſuperſtition; that, as the prouerbe hath it, bee merry, but wiſe; ſo ſay we, be as zealous as you will, but yet accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to wiſdome and ſobriety; for though a man can neuer bee too zealous, yet he may be ſomtimes <note place="margin">Rom. 12. 3</note> too ſuperſtitious. But alas, there be too many now a dayes, that doe not hold this head, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake to the Coloſſians concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the worſhip of Saints and Angels; and wee ſpeake this to <note place="margin">Col. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 18.</note> their ſhame, eſpecially the Prieſts
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:14464:38"/>
and Leuites, who hold all that they haue, <hi>in capite,</hi> and this, we ſay, is the ſureſt hold, for it was <hi>Platoes</hi> tenet, with ſome other, that in this member was the ſeat of life and being. But ſure I am, <note place="margin">Democritus.</note> that in holding Chriſt the head of our faith, wee ſhall liue for euer, ſince eternall life is in him, ſaies <note place="margin">1 Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 5. 12.</note> the Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>And ſo much for the firſt thing requiſite in the manner of our fight, which is wiſdome.</p>
            <p>The ſecond followes, and this is ſtrength and courage, for I doe not meane heere ſo much the ſtrength of the hand, as that of the heart, when with <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt, we haue <hi>Ceur de Lyon,</hi> a <note place="margin">S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Chron.</note> Lions heart, that will not be dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: and therefore <hi>Socrates</hi> being asked what ſtrength was, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that it was <hi>motus animae cum corpore,</hi> for if ſtrength bee defici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:14464:38"/>
alas what ſhall become of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; it ſhall be, me thinks, like a child that is come to the birth, but for want of ſtrength, cannot be deliuered, as <hi>Hezekiah</hi> ſpake in <note place="margin">Iſa. 37. 3.</note> another caſe. For as ſtrength without wiſdome is wanting in the noble diſpoſition of warlike ſtratagems, ſo alſo is wiſdome without ſtrength failing in the due execution of the ſame: wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome indeed may ſerue to guide, but it is ſtrength and courage that muſt defend our ſelues, and offend our enemies.</p>
            <p>And therefore <hi>Dauid</hi> being now ready to leaue the world, leaues this to his ſonne <hi>Solomon,</hi> as his laſt gift and legacy, <hi>Bee ſtrong,</hi> ſaies he, <hi>and of a good cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>and thou ſhalt proſper:</hi> and ſurely it was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a gift worthy of ſuch a giuer.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Iphicrates</hi> then had it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim'd
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:14464:39"/>
to his ſouldiers before the vndertaking of any hard exploit, If any man haue left his heart at h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et him fling downe his colors and bee gone. Or as <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deon</hi> ſaid, <hi>If any man be fearfull, let</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 7. 3.</note> 
               <hi>him depart;</hi> ſo ſay I, if there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny white liuer'd Chriſtian among vs, who for a tearme of diſgrace, or a little blaſt of oppoſition can be content with <hi>Peter</hi> to deny his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors of Chriſtianity, <hi>abeat, pereat, profundat, perdat;</hi> away with ſuch <note place="margin">Ter. Heaut.</note> a wretch, but withall let him, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out repentance, periſh eternally. We read of Chriſt our Captain, that he could endure the Croſſe, and deſpiſe the ſhame, to runne on <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 1.</note> the race that was ſet before him: <hi>And let as many of vs,</hi> ſaies the ſame Apoſtle, <hi>as would be perfect, looke vp to Ieſus the author and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſher of our faith:</hi> conſider him who broke through ſuch contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:14464:39"/>
of ſinners, and by him bee encouraged to reſiſt vnto blood, ſtriuing againſt ſinne, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, and not to <note place="margin">verſ 4.</note> deny our innocency to the death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quid enim deſperandum Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto Duce?</hi> for what need we feare, hauing ſuch a Captain, <hi>who for our ſakes hath led away captiuity</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ph. 4 8.</note> 
               <hi>captiue,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeakes, and hath cruſhed in peeces the very head of the maligning world: <hi>for bee of good comfort,</hi> ſaies our Sauiour, <hi>I haue ouercome the world; Et licet atrocitèr lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quantur,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 16. 33</note> ſaies <hi>Tacitus</hi> of <hi>Vitelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> ſouldiers, <hi>minor eſt tamen apud victos animus.</hi> And an enemy, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hiſt. li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 3.</note> wee know, that is once beaten, though he ſpeake big for a time, yet if he come once to ſtrokes, his courage will then quickly faint and quaile. Only let that exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Apoſtle take place
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:14464:40"/>
with vs, <hi>To lift vp our hands that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1.</note> 
               <hi>hang downe, and our feeble knees;</hi> yea, our hearts alſo that hang downe towards our feet, ſaying with <hi>Dauid, I will not feare though ten thouſand of enemies doe bande</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal 3. 6. So a cow and is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, <hi>cuius a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus in pedious.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>themſelues againſt mee,</hi> or with <hi>Paul</hi> ſend forth that triumphant challenge, <hi>What ſhall bee able to ſeparate me from the loue of God in Chriſt? ſhall tribulation or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh? &amp;c. No, I am perſwaded</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 38</note> 
               <hi>that neither life nor death, no nor any thing elſe ſhall euer bee able to ſeparate mee from the loue of God in Chriſt.</hi> And then good luck haue we with our honour, as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> hath it, <hi>Ride on becauſe of the word of truth and meekneſſe, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 45. 4.</note> 
               <hi>our right hands ſhall teach vs ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible things.</hi> The campe of Chriſt will admit of no weakling, of no daſtard; and hence it is that S. <hi>Paul</hi> in his Panoply ſpeaks of no
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:14464:40"/>
armour atall for our back parts, <note place="margin">Eph. 6. 12.</note> but only for thoſe that are before; to ſhew that hee would not haue vs afraid to looke our enemies in the face, but to quit our ſelues like men, and be ſtrong: and not <note place="margin">1 Co. vlt. 13</note> to be like thoſe of Ephraim, who turn'd their backs in the day of <note place="margin">Pſa. 78. 10.</note> battell: for, <hi>ſhall ſuch a man as I fly,</hi> ſaies <hi>Nehemiah, I will neuer</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Neh. 6. 11.</note> 
               <hi>doe it.</hi> Indeed I muſt needs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that in our earthly warfare wee oft times become ſtrong by making our ſelues weake, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome our enemies, like the Parthian, by flying from them: But in our ſpirituall warfare it is not thus <hi>Reſiſt the Deuill,</hi> ſaies S. <hi>Peter, and then hee will flee from</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 5. 9.</note> 
               <hi>you:</hi> but if we fly from him firſt, thereby hoping for the greater aduantage, then <hi>acriùs urget ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis,</hi> the enemy will come with the greater violence, <hi>becauſe wee wra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:14464:41"/>
not,</hi> as they doe, <hi>againſt fleſh and blood,</hi> ſaies <hi>Paul, but againſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eph. 6. 12.</note> 
               <hi>principalities and powers, and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall wickedneſſes in high places;</hi> and therefore as they can the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſcry our purpoſes, ſo will they alſo preuent our practiſes, as well <hi>knowing whereof we are made, and remembring how wee bee but duſt.</hi>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But enough for the ſecond re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite in the manner of our fight, and this is ſtrength or courage.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The third and laſt followes, which is conſtancy and perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; and this muſt ſtrike the battell through, &amp; make vp of all the former flowers a complete garland of triumph.</p>
            <p>For as Chriſt ſaid to the yong <note place="margin">Mar. 10. 21</note> man who profeſſ'd that hee had kept all the commandments from his youth; ſo ſay I now to you
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:14464:41"/>
that haue vſed all thoſe other meanes from the beginning of your dayes, <hi>unum adhuc ſupereſt,</hi> there is yet one thing wanting to perfection, and this is conſtancy in them to the end of your daies. For as <hi>finis</hi> doth <hi>movere ad pug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandum,</hi> ſo doth it alſo <hi>poſt pug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandum exhibere coronam,</hi> as it doth prouoke vs to fight at the firſt, ſo alſo doth it reward vs for fighting at the laſt; <hi>for no man is crown'd,</hi> ſaies the Apoſtle, <hi>vnleſſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 1.</note> 
               <hi>he ſtriue firſt:</hi> and as wee are not crown'd vnleſſe we ſtriue firſt, ſo neither vnleſſe we ſtriue laſt, euen to the laſt period of the battell, <hi>fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis enim coronat opus,</hi> for the end is euer that which crownes the action; ſo ſaies our Sauiour to the Miniſter of the Church of <hi>Smyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, Be faithfull to death, and then will I giue thee a crowne of life.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Reu. 2. 10.</note> And this was the reaſon why
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:14464:42"/>
God commanded, that vpon the outward skirts and end of <hi>Aarons</hi> garments there ſhould bee Pome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>granates of blew ſilke and purple, becauſe of all other fruits doth the <note place="margin">Ex. 28 33.</note> Pomegranate beare moſt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance of a crowne vpon it; ſo that as <hi>Dauid</hi> hath it, the oyle of grace muſt runne downe from our heads, euen to our beards; and not reſt there neither, vntill it hath touched the end of the combate, the skirts of our clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: <note place="margin">Pſa. 133. 2.</note> and therefore it is lamented by the Prophet touching <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> that her filthineſſe was in her skirts, and her end was worſe then <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1. 9.</note> her beginning. <hi>But if any man turne his hands to the plow,</hi> ſaies Chriſt, <hi>and looke back againe, ſuch a one is not fit for the kingdome of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 9. 60.</note> 
               <hi>heauen. Neither ſhall my ſoule,</hi> ſaies God, <hi>haue pleaſure in him.</hi> We muſt not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for the word is <note place="margin">Heb. 10. 38</note>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:14464:42"/>
vſed by S. <hi>Luke,</hi> and ſignifies pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, to ſhrinke back, as coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">Luk. 18. 1.</note> ſouldiers doe in warre, when there is apparent feare of danger, and ſo it is noted in the margent of your <hi>Edward</hi> Bibles.</p>
            <p>It is but an hypocriticall tricke to enter into the performance of <note place="margin">Sir <hi>Francis Bacon. In Charles the 8. his expedition, on which ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them to a flea, ſoone skip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing into a countrey, &amp; as ſoone out Heylen. Hiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Gen 15. 11</note> good duties, as a ſtranger doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an Inne, or as the French did ſometimes into Italy, as one ſaid of them wittily, onely to chalke vp their lodgings and bee gone; But a true Chriſtian Souldier, he will alway deale with his ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all enemies, as <hi>Abraham</hi> did with the fowles that lighted vpon his ſacrifice, neuer leaue driuing them away vntill the euening: hee will wreſtle with them as earneſtly as euer <hi>Iacob</hi> did with the Angell, <note place="margin">Gen. 32. 22</note> euen til the day of ſaluation break, and the ſhadowes of the night flee away: Which if we doe, then
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:14464:43"/>
ſhall we be truly called, as our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was before vs, The Iſrael of God, becauſe wee haue fought with our enemies, and preuailed. There now wants nothing but <hi>Pauls</hi> deſire, and then may the <note place="margin">Phil. 1. 23 <hi>Cupio diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolui, &amp;c.</hi> Iſa. 40. 1.</note> company be <hi>diſſolued, and be with Chriſt. Then ſpeake comfortably to Ieruſalem,</hi> ſaith the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> in the perſon of God, <hi>and tell her that her warfare is accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed: For now ſhall our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe go before vs,</hi> as the ſame <note place="margin">Iſa. 58. 8.</note> Prophet ſpeakes in another place, <hi>and the glory of God ſhall be our reward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, now ſhall be brought to paſſe the ſaying that is written:
<q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We haue fought a good fight, we haue fulfilled our courſe, we</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2. Tim. 4. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>haue runne our race, we haue continued in the faith, hence
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:14464:43"/>
forth therefore is laid vp for vs a Crowne of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Which God giue vs, for Ieſus Chriſt our onely Lord and Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS:</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
